These mushrooms and bacteria are both ancient beings.
You might think of them as a delightful addition to your tagliatelle or as a beautiful accent on
top of your pizza, but did you ever think that mushrooms could actually just be aliens? If you
were an alien species looking to survive for billions of years and trying to travel
intergalactically without dying out, would you choose to look like a foreign invader or would
you merge with higher life forms and affect the way they act and think in a way that promotes
your survival? But let's back up, like two billion years back up. Ancient fungi emerged on earth at
least 2.4 billion years ago. This was before plants and animals even existed. In fact, we're descended
from mushrooms. Animals split off from fungi about 650 million years ago. A lot of pharmaceuticals
use fungi, but we're also super prone to fungal diseases, so it's a blessing and a curse. For this
otherworldly topic, I brought in one of my best friends, Taro Issacopola, the founder and
CEO of Taro, the founder and CEO of Taro, the founder and CEO of Taro, the founder and CEO of
Taro, the founder and CEO of Taro, the founder and CEO of Taro, the founder and CEO of Four Sigmatic, maybe
the seminal consumer mushroom brand in the US. So I make Jesse a very simple smoothie,
filtered water, fresh blueberries, and protein powder. Taro is a very interesting guy. A fungi,
some might say. We actually met while one of us was on shrooms, adaptogenic ones of course,
so you might say fungal intelligence brought us together. We've quickly become best friends,
and since then, I've learned a ton from Taro on life, business, and of course, fungi.
That's one of my spirit animals, a whale. They can have sex for 30 hours in a row while singing.
That's pretty sweet, man.
One of the trippiest things Taro has ever said in my presence that has always
stuck with me was in a conversation we had two years ago with the mycologist,
Merlin Sheldrake, the author of the great bestselling book, Entangled Life.
Not just mushrooms, but other really sacred foods tend to live in these, like the beginning
of the forest life cycle, or at the end of the forest life cycle, where there's extremely nothing
else growing almost, like pioneer, or at the end of it when there's massive biodiversity.
Can mushrooms essentially act as consciousness capsules,
preserving consciousness from the end of one life to the beginning of the next?
Why do they show up first in the most harsh environments and after catastrophic destruction?
It's almost as if they're zip files with the ability to download life before cataclysmic
events, carry it through hostile environments, and reboot it elsewhere. This got me thinking
about a book that I've always loved called Chariots of the Gods by Eric Von Daniken.
The book was released in 1968 and became an international sensation. The premise was that
ancient alien astronauts came down to earth around 10,000 years ago at the time of the agrarian
revolution and taught us how to basically start modern civilization.
When the extraterrestrials left some thousands of years ago,
they promised to our forefathers, we will return.
Von Daniken points to astronomically aligned architecture that we could never build with a
telescope without advanced knowledge of the stars, Mayan cave paintings depicting astronauts,
and Sumerian artifacts that show the solar system in its proper alignment
thousands of years before we developed telescopes.
But the idea got laughed off by mainstream academia.
These things were built by the men and women who lived at that time in that country.
I once organized a lunch with Von Daniken that Joe Rogan attended.
I had lunch with Eric Von Daniken last week.
Oh my god.
Yes.
What's the real story there? I was wondering.
Sigh.
Mostly nonsense.
Clearly Rogan was a bit skeptical too.
Von Daniken might be wrong, but his book sold so well because it hit a latent, unarticulated sense
that the story we tell ourselves about the origins of humanity isn't quite right.
Human homo sapiens have been physiologically the same for roughly 200,000 years.
So why in the last 5% of our existence, just 10,000 years ago,
did we somehow just figure out agriculture, history, religion, and culture?
How did this just spontaneously happen all of a sudden?
Scientists might call
the origin of culture something like an emergent phenomena.
As soon as we figured out agriculture, we just had more time to do other things,
like write things down, read, tell stories, and start culture.
But does more leisure time automatically mean more culture?
I'm not so sure.
But there are even more unexplainable gaps in human history.
The human brain literally doubled in size from homo habilis 2 million years ago
to homo sapiens 200,000 years ago.
Evolutionary biologists like to explain this away with a phenomena they call punctuated equilibria,
and so is to leave homo sapiens perched smugly on the top run.
Eldridge and Gould called their new pattern punctuated equilibria.
Okay, maybe alien astronaut theory is too crazy.
But these other theories are kind of lame, just placeholder theories
that don't actually say or predict anything new.
They're just terms we invented to make it seem like we understand anomalous things
that we actually don't know the first thing about.
Here's an alternative theory.
Maybe something has been guiding man's physiological and cultural evolution behind the scenes.
A stroke of fungal inspiration.
A spore from the heavens.
Okay, I know that's a lot to digest.
But if you need some adaptogenic assistance, today's American Alchemist and his company
might be able to help.
You have to try it.
In the meantime, please enjoy this episode with my very good friend, Taro Hissokopoulos.
Different parts of the brain have different activities.
But you know that, don't you?
People like you do a lot.
Maybe you should interview me.
The questions remain.
This is a journey into sound.
Do you think they spawned modern human civilization?
They definitely were here before.
They definitely have intelligence.
And they've definitely been part of the story from humanity from day one.
Panspermia is the idea that life on Earth was germinated by microbes from outer space.
In fact, in 1973, Francis Crick, who discovered the double helical structure of DNA, decided
to write a paper on directed panspermia.
I'm going to take this theory one step further.
And say that mushrooms not only seeded humanity, but they've been guiding our evolution until
today.
Before you accuse me of madness, consider these three facts.
Number one, mushrooms have dramatic effects on our bodies and minds.
Number two, mushroom spores can travel through space.
Number three, and perhaps the most important point, is that mushrooms provide a way better
explanation for those questions I brought up earlier about the dramatic doubling in
size of the human brain, as well as the origin of human culture.
We know there's a very strong mind-gut connection.
In fact, we call the gut our second brain.
It contains 500 million neurons.
Microbes in the gut create many essential neurotransmitters.
In fact, 95% of our serotonin actually lives in the gut.
And the vagus nerve communicates between the gut and the brain all the time.
It's scientifically conventional and mainstream at this point to say that the microbiome has
a profound effect on our mental state.
But the microbiome cannot exist without a mycobiome.
Everyone has function.
Everyone has fungus in their gut accompanying bacteria.
If you don't think mushrooms can influence the minds of their hosts, look no further
than this video.
Spores from a parasitic fungus called cordyceps have infiltrated their bodies and their minds.
Bullet ants in the Amazon eat cordyceps mushrooms, which co-opt their brains and movements and
literally mind control them onto higher ground where a fruiting body sprouts from the head
of the ants.
Cordyceps can wipe out entire ant colonies.
I mean, it's easy to say things in nature like that are completely autonomic.
They're not, they're not conscious, but it does feel like there's some sort of intentionality
around sustainability.
You have slime mold, sort of, if you put scat in the shape of the Japanese subway system,
the slime mold can figure out a more efficient route than the actual Japanese subway system.
Do we know whose agenda is it?
Is it the mushroom's agenda?
Is it a more holistic being and mushrooms are the servants of that higher being?
I don't know.
I think that they're selfish, but at the same time, they're selfish through a lens
of like harmony.
Next, we can look at magic mushrooms or psilocybin.
Ego dissolution, which some refer to as the mystical experience.
I actually think they're pretty much the same thing.
One is a spiritual vocabulary, one is a psychodynamic vocabulary.
We all know that psilocybin has profound effects on our consciousness and lingering ones on
our thought process and neural patterns too.
We know that it lowers activity in the DNA.
We know that it lowers activity in the brain.
We know that it lowers activity in a brain.
So the fact that it's a default mode network, which is the anterior and posterior singlet
of your brain, this inhibits connections made by other parts of your brain.
Reports of selflessness correlate with reports of lower activity in this part of the brain.
Having had a taste of that other form of consciousness where you're not the victim of your loops
of destructive thought can be liberating.
Couldn't other ones, even non-psychedelic mushrooms, have similar mental effects?
Four Sigmatic has served more than 100 million servings of mushrooms to the world.
That's amazing.
We never thought mushrooms were that much more dangerous.
to use things like chaga and reishi within like six months they make a major life change
remember those bad placeholder theories that we had to explain away the stepwise leap in brain
size that humans have seen over the last two million years and the crazy spontaneous origin
of human culture mushrooms explain both of these open questions way better for this explanation we
should again refer back to ethnobotanist and fungal philosopher terence mckenna he basically
posited that human hunter-gathering tribes a couple million years back in africa would have
to follow animal poop in order to find their prey and what grew on this animal poop you guessed it
psilocybin i believe that god left certain drugs growing naturally upon our planet to help speed up
and facilitate our evolution psilocybin substitutes the serotonin becomes a better neurotransmitter
activates neurogenesis give up your mycophobia or even your
xylophobia and just look at as a serious scientific analysis so hunter-gatherers probably
took a lot of magic mushrooms leading to neurogenesis new neural pathways and epigenetic
changes in their brain which they probably passed down to their offspring could this have accounted
for the doubling in brain size that humans have seen over the last two million years
maybe but what about the creation of modern culture ten thousand years ago is really when
modern history religion writing and stationary living began for
people to look at the
past and the present i thought for a fact that they could predict the future of their own life
or i'll be honest i had not been doing any of my research on this as a kid for years but the answers
as to why all these things popped up so quickly we might have to look to a little book called
Kekion probably contained ergot, a psychedelic fungus. But here's the crazy part. Ergot is a
substance that specifically infects wheat and barley, two crops that we definitely grew in
the agrarian revolution. It makes sense that we'd start consuming ergot after we started growing
these crops. So maybe psychedelics played an instrumental role in the creation of western
philosophy, governance, and rationality. But Brian also mentions archaeologically excavated
chalices at Gobekli Tepe, which dates back to 12,000 years ago, right before the agrarian
revolution. He hypothesizes that ancient burial rituals probably went on at Gobekli Tepe and that
these chalices might have been involved in those rituals and contained ergot too. So maybe
agriculture did have something to do with the origins of culture. It just wasn't necessarily
the extra time that farming freed up that allowed culture to flourish. It was literally the fungus
growing on the agriculture that affected our consciousness in profile.
The fact that like psychedelics or mind-altering substances have not been part of pretty much
every ancient civilization would be really weird. And then there's a lot of like weird
connections that got like washed. This is Tara's latest book. A lot of people think Santa Claus is
Saint Nicholas, but it's clearly not. If you follow the roots, like how it came to the U.S. through
New York, through the Dutch, the Dutch had Sinterklaas, their own version of Santa Claus. The
Dutch got it from the Germans.
The Germans got it from Italians. The Italians stole the grave of Saint Nicholas, who was again
Turkish. There's no reindeers in Turkey. And the Turkish then got it from the Slavics. And the
Slavic got it from this semi-nomadic reindeer herders called the Sami, which are the people that
live with the reindeer. So it's very logical. Some connections between the Sami people and
the story of Santa Claus are the following. Christmas presents are always presented under
the tree. Under the trees in Lapland, where the Sami people live, grows one of the most famous
mushrooms in the world. Santa Claus is a very famous mushroom. Santa Claus is a very famous
mushroom in the world. And the Giants entsprechend the famous mushroom form. So people, just as
other figures, eat mushrooms when they'reoney, having some fun. Yeah. And joy in Los Angeles.
May the God of Isis and God of The Un voice over the last few steppes of the Christ Course which
lead to the Sśmyn belt, amen? Mm. Mm. What else's upties? So, Christmas presents are
the topic where the climate change is really critical at this point in the year. Now, did
and through the chimney not to mention the sami wore red and white their shoes are pretty damn
near elf shoes and they lived very close to the north pole and there's all these like
connection points with the santa claus story but fundamentally has traveled through multiple
generations it's like probably eight to ten thousand years old and at the core of it is
taking a psychedelic and thinking about death christmas and filthy animals but finally for
mushrooms to be aliens they have to be able to travel through space which is impossible right
wrong they've actually been found growing on the international space station and on the russian
mirror space station mushroom spores are incredibly resilient they're extremophiles
that can withstand high radiation environments in fact an intact fossil of a 1.4 billion year
old mushroom was found in northeastern brazil so if an alien civilization wanted to send some
mushroom spores our way across space it wouldn't necessarily be impossible the
great great great great great great great great great great great great great great great great
carl sagan knowing that mushrooms could travel through space was actually somewhat skeptical
that they could travel intergalactically and remain viable but if they hybridize themselves
with higher life forms everywhere maybe they came here on a spaceship this was francis crick's top
candidate for a most likely explanation of panspermia in his paper he thought that a
high-tech spaceship with blue algae co2 and water for sustenance could have been sent with mushrooms
on board to spawn life on earth perhaps mushrooms have been grooming us since day
one and that's why we're here today we're here because we're here because we're here because we're
here because we're here because we're here because we're here because we're here because we're here
because we're here because we're here because we're here because we're here because we're here
subtly influencing our technological progress so that we in turn can take them to other planets
take a look at this passage from terence mckenna's true hallucinations where he recounts to the best
of his abilities what the mushrooms are trying to communicate to him within my memory is the
knowledge of hyperlight drive ships and how to build them i will trade this knowledge for
a free ticket to new worlds around suns less forsaken so are mushrooms guiding us to the
stars do they want to use us as chauffeurs to help them germinate elsewhere maybe mushrooms
Mushroom cosmic wisdom took root in our brains and were their best shot at a galactic hitchhike.
So what the hell does all this mean?
For starters, as a society we should do far more research into the mycobiome and its effect
on human consciousness and performance.
On a personal level, we should cut out and be cognizant of bad mushrooms like candida
and mold and try to ingest more good mushrooms like chaga, reishi, and lion's mane.
This is Tarot's and Four Sigmatic's mission.
When it comes to life on Earth, fungi are the OG.
They're the overlords, the landlords, and the janitors of the planet.
We should heed their ancient wisdom if we wish to renew our tenancy on this rock.
I hope you enjoyed today's episode.
Tell me what you think.
Did mushroom spores spawn human life on Earth?
Are mushrooms consciousness capsules that transcend human mortality?
Leave a comment and hit subscribe for more crazy content like this.
Until next time, I'm Jesse Michaels and this is American Alchemy.